[Music]
Reedman reads
the Giver by Lois Lowry, narrated by Fraser Reedman.
Chapter 17.
[Music]
TODAY IS DECLARED AN UNSCHEDULED HOLIDAY..
Jonas,, his parents,, and Lily all turned in surprise and looked at the wall
speaker from which the announcement had come.. It happened so rarely. It was such
a treat for the entire community when it did.. Adults were exempted from the day's
work,, children from school and training and volunteer hours.. The substitute
Laborers, who would be given a different holiday, took over all the necessary
tasks:, nurturing,, food delivery,, and care of the Old;, and the community was
free.. Jonas cheered, and put his homework folder down. He'd been about to leave
for school.. School was less important to him now;, and before much more time
passed,, his formal schooling would end.
still,, for Twelves,, though they'd begun their adult training,, there were still
the endless lists of rules to be memorized, and the newest technology to
be mastered.. He wished his parents,, sister,, and Gabe a happy day,, and rode
down the bicycle path,, looking for Asher.. He had not taken the pills, now,
for 4 weeks.. The Stirrings had returned,, and he felt a little guilty and
embarrassed about the pleasurable dreams that came to him as he slept.. But he
knew he couldn't go back to the world of no feelings that he had lived in for so
long., And his new, heightened feelings permeated a greater realm than simply
asleep. Though he knew that his failure to take the pills accounted for some of
it,, he thought that the feelings came also from the memories..
Now he could see all of the colors; and he could keep them, too, so that the trees
and grass and bushes stayed green in his vision.. Gabriel's rosy cheeks stayed
pink, even when he slept. And apples were always, always red.. Now, through the
memories, he had seen oceans and mountain lakes and streams that gurgled through
woods;. and now he saw the familiar wide river beside the path differently.. He
saw all of the light and color and history it contained and carried in its
slowmoving water;. and he knew there was an Elsewhere from which it came, and an
Elsewhere to which it was going..
On this unexpected, casual holiday, he felt happy, as he always had on holidays;,
but with a deeper happiness than ever before.. Thinking, as he always did, about
precision of language,, Jonas realized that it was a new depth of feelings that
he was experiencing.. Somehow they were not at all the same as the feelings that
every evening, in every dwelling, every citizen analyzed with endless talk.. ""I
felt angry because someone broke the play area rules,"," Lily had said once,,
making a fist with her small hand to indicate her fury.. Her family—, —Jonas
among them—, —had talked about the possible reasons for rulebreaking, and
the need for understanding and patience,, until Lily's fist had relaxed, and her
anger was gone.. But Lily had not felt anger,, Jonas realized now.. Shallow
impatience and exasperation,. that was all Lily had felt.. He knew that was
certainty because now he knew what anger was.. Now he had, in the memories,
experienced injustice and cruelty,, and he had reacted with rage that welled up
so passionately inside him that the thought of discussing it calmly at the
evening meal was unthinkable.. ""I felt sad today,"," he had heard his mother say,,
and then comforted her.. But now Jonas had experienced real sadness.. He had
felt grief.. He knew that there was no quick comfort for emotions like those..
These were deeper, and they did not need to be told.. They were felt.. Today,, he
felt happiness..
"Asher!". He spied his friend's bicycle leaning against a tree at the edge of
the playing field.. Nearby,, other bikes were strewn about on the ground.. On a
holiday, the usual rules of order could be disregarded.. He skidded to a stop and
dropped his own bike beside the others..
""Hey,, Ash!"!" he shouted,, looking around..
There seemed to be no one in the play area.. "Where are you?
A child's voice, coming from behind a nearby bush, made the sound.. "Pow!! Pow!!
Pow!"! A female 11 named Tanya staggered forward from where she'd been hiding..
Dramatically, she clutched her stomach and stumbled about in a zigzag pattern,,
groaning.. ""You got me!"!" she called, and fell to the ground,, grinning.. ""Blam!"!"
Jonas,, standing on the side of the playing field,, recognized Asher's voice..
He saw his friend, aiming an imaginary weapon in his hand, dart from behind one
tree to another.. "Blam!. You're in my line of ambush,, Jonas!. Watch out!". Jonas
stepped back.. He moved behind Asher's bike and knelt so that he was out of
sight.. It was a game he had often played with the other children,. a game of good
guys and bad guys,. a harmless pastime that used up their contained energy and
ended only when they all lay posed in freakish postures on the ground.. He had
never recognized it before as a game of war..
"Attack!". The shout came from behind the small storehouse where play equipment
was kept.. Three children dashed forward, their imaginary weapons in firing
position.. From the opposite side of the field came an opposing shout, "Counter
attack!" From their hiding places. a horde of children—. —Jonas recognized
Fiona in the group— —emerged,, running in a crouch position,, firing across the
field.. Several of them stopped,, grabbed their own shoulders and chest with
exaggerated gestures,, and pretended to be hit.. They dropped to the ground and
lay suppressing giggles..
Feelings surged within Jonas.. He found himself walking forward into the field..
""You're hit,, Jonas!"!" Asher yelled from behind the tree.. ""Pow!, You're hit
again!"." Jonas stood alone in the center of the field.. Several of the children
raised their heads and looked at him uneasily.. The attacking armies slowed,,
emerged from their crouch positions,, and watched to see what he was doing.. In his
mind,, Jonas saw again the face of the boy who had lain dying on a field and
had begged him for water.. He had a sudden choking feeling, as if it were
difficult to breathe.. One of the children raised an imaginary rifle and
made an attempt to destroy him with a firing noise.
Then they were all silent,, standing awkwardly,, and the only sound was the
sound of Jonas's shuddering breaths.. He was struggling not to cry.. Gradually,,
when nothing happened,, nothing changed,.
the children looked at each other nervously and went away.. He heard the
sounds as they rided their bicycles and began to ride down the path that led
from the field.. Only Asher and Fiona remained.. ""What's wrong,, Jonas?? It was
only a game,"," Fiona said.. ""You ruined it,"," Asher said in an irritated voice..
""Don't play it anymore,"," Jonas pleaded..
""I'm the one who's training for Assistant Recreation Director,"," Asher
pointed out angrily.. ""Games aren't your area of expertness."."
"Expertise,". Jonas corrected him automatically.. "Whatever.. You can't say
what we play, even if you are going to be the new Receiver.". Asher looked wearily
at him.. "I apologize for not paying you the respect you deserve,". he mumbled..
"Asher,". Jonas said. He was trying to speak carefully, and with kindness, to say
exactly what he wanted to say.. "You had no way of knowing this.. I didn't know it
myself until recently.. But it's a cruel game.. In the past, there have—" "I said I
apologize, Jonas.". Jonas sighed.. It was no use.. Of course, Asher couldn't
understand.. "I accept your apology,, Asher,", he said wearily.. "Do you want to
go for a ride along the river,, Jonas?"?
Fiona asked,, biting her lip with nervousness.. Jonas looked at her.. She
was so lovely.. For a fleeting instant, he thought he would like nothing better
than to ride peacefully along the river path,, laughing and talking with his
gentle female friend.. But he knew that such times had been taken from him now..
He shook his head.. After a moment, his two friends turned and went to their
bikes.. He watched as they rode away..
Jonas trudged to the bench beside the Storehouse and sat down,, overwhelmed
with feelings of loss., His childhood,, his friendships,, his carefree sense of
security—. —all these things seemed to be slipping away.. With his new, heightened
feelings,, he was overwhelmed by sadness at the way others had laughed and
shouted,, playing at war.. But he knew that they could not understand why,.
without the memories.. He felt such love for Asher and for Fiona, they could not
feel it back, without the memories., And he could not give them those..
Jonas knew with certainty that he could change nothing.. Back in their dwelling,
that evening,, Lily chattered merrily about the wonderful holiday she had had,,
playing with her friends,, having her midday meal out of doors,, and (she
confessed), sneaking a very short try on her father's bicycle.. "I can't wait till
I get my very own bicycle next month..
Father's is too big for me.. I fell,"," she explained matterofactly. "Good thing
Gabe wasn't in the child's seat!". "A very good thing,"," Mother agreed,, frowning at
the idea of it.. Gabriel waved his arms at the mention of himself.. "He had begun
to walk just a week before.. The first steps of a new child were always the
occasion for celebration at the Nurturing Center,," Father said,, but also
for the introduction of a discipline wand.. Now, Father brought the slender
instrument home with him each night, in case Gabriel misbehaved.. But he was a
happy and easygoing toddler.. Now he moved unsteadily across the room,, laughing..
"Gay!", he chirped.. "Gay!". It was the way he said his own name.. Jonas brightened.. It
had been a depressing day for him, after such a bright start., But he set his glum
thoughts aside.. He thought about starting to teach Lily to ride so that
she could speed off proudly after her Ceremony of Nine,, which would be coming
soon.. It was hard to believe that it was almost December again,, that almost a
year had passed since he had become a 12. He smiled as he watched the new
child plant one small foot carefully before the other,, grinning with glee at
his own steps as he tried them out.. ""I want to get to sleep early tonight,","
Father said. "Tomorrow is a big day for me.. The twins are being born tomorrow,,
and the test results show that they're identical.". "One for here,, one for
Elsewhere,"," Lily chanted.. ""One for here,, one for Else—"." ""Do you actually take it
Elsewhere,, Father?"?" Jonas asked.. ""No,, I just have to make the selection..
I weigh them,, hand the larger over to the Nurturer who's standing by,, waiting,.
and then I get the smaller one all cleaned up and comfy.. Then I perform a
small Ceremony of Release, and—" —"He glanced down,, grinning at Gabriel.. "Then
I wave bye-bye,", he said, in the special, sweet voice he used when he spoke to the
new child. He waved his hand in the familiar gesture.. Gabriel giggled and
waved bye-bye back to him.. "And somebody else comes to get him?? Somebody from
Elsewhere?"? "That's right, Jonas. Bonus.
Jonas rolled his eyes in embarrassment that his father had used the silly pet
name.. Lily was deep in thought.. "What if they give the little twin a name
Elsewhere,? a name like maybe Jonathan?.
And here, in our community, at his naming,, the twin that we kept here is given the
name Jonathan,. and then there would be two children with the same name,. and
they would look exactly the same,. and someday, maybe they were a Six,. one group
of Sixes would go to visit another community on a bus, and and there in the
other community, the other group of Sixes, would be a Jonathan who was
exactly the same as the other Jonathan,.
and then maybe they would get mixed up and take the wrong Jonathan home, and
maybe his parents wouldn't notice,. and then—" She paused for a breath.. "Lily,",
Mother said,, "I have a wonderful idea..
Maybe when you become a 12, they'll give you the Assignment of Storyteller!. I
don't think we've had a Storyteller in the community for a long time.. But if I
were on the Committee,, I would definitely choose you for that job!". Lily
grinned.. "I have a better idea for one more story,", she announced..
"What if actually we were all twins and didn't know it,? and so Elsewhere there
would be another Lily, and another Jonas, and another Father, and another Asher, and
another Chief Elder, and another—" Father groaned.. "Lily,", he said., "It's bedtime.
[Music]